<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<language>
  <page id="698008001" title="Lacuna Notebook General Info" descr="" voice="no">
    <!-- In-Encyclopedia Category Name -->
    <t id="99">Lacuna Notebook</t>
    <!-- Left Sidebar Button Name -->
    <t id="2400">Lacuna Notebook</t>
    <t id="2401">The Lacuna Notebook contains community provided information to further explain game topics not covered in the in-game documentation</t>
    <!-- Detail/References Pane Title-->
    <t id="2404">References</t>
    <!-- Top Level Menu Button Name -->
    <t id="8104">Lacuna Notebook</t>
    <t id="8107">The Lacuna Notebook contains knowledge that you have acquired and lists historic events on a timeline.</t>
    <!-- Menu Title -->
    <t id="9000">Encyclopedia + Lacuna Notebook</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008002" title="Lacuna Notebook Categories" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">Welcome to Lacuna Notebook</t>
    <t id="2">698008003</t>
    <t id="3">New Player Guide [Part 1]</t>
    <t id="4">698008004</t>
    <t id="5">New Player Guide [Part 2]</t>
    <t id="6">698008005</t>
    <t id="7">Returning Player Information</t>
    <t id="8">698008006</t>
    <t id="9">Misc Guides</t>
    <t id="10">698008007</t>
    <t id="11">Spoilers - You Know You Want to Peak Inside</t>
    <t id="12">698008008</t>
    <t id="13">Homeless Content</t>
    <t id="14">698008009</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008003" title="Lacuna Notebook Welcome to Lacuna Notebook Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">Start Here</t>
    <t id="2">The goal of the Lacuna Notebook is to provide information that will help players get the\nmost out of their playthrough.  X4 is big, complicated, and obfuscated by lack of\ninstruction.  \n\nThe information provided in the Notebook entries tries to fill the gaps of in-game\ndocumentation but it will also include spoilers.  If the entry has spoiler information,\nit will have a [Spolier] tag at the beginning of the title.  A best-effort will be made\nto note if any entry has spoilers but sometimes it could be matter of opinion.  \n\nThe format of the entries is in Markdown style.  X4 has no support for rendering \nMarkdown content, but all the entries in the Notebook come from Markdown documents.  \nMore information can be viewed in the entries:\n\n* Viewing Entries Offline\n* Customizing Entries\n\nThis notebook is my first mod and is basically a copy of the Encyclopedia with code\nbolted on for Lacuna Notebook.  All the functionality and content of the vanilla\nEncyclopedia is in Lacuna Notebook also.\n\nThere is so much content I want to add that the organization of it will likely change\nas more entries get added.  I also want to make sure this mod doesn't break anything but\nno refunds :\)!  Expect lots, no, tons of typo, grammatical, and formatting errors to, no\nwait, too I mean...\n\nIf wondering where to go next, here are a couple of categories to visit next:\n\n* For new players, open up "New to X4"\n* For returning players, open up "Returning to X4"</t>
    <t id="3">Searching Information</t>
    <t id="4">* The search function works just like the one in the Encyclopedia\n* Searches are done only on the title of an entry, not the body/contents of it</t>
    <t id="5">Avoiding Spoilers</t>
    <t id="6">* A best-effort will be made to include the [Spoiler] tag in the title of any entry that\n  may have a spoiler</t>
    <t id="7">Known Issues with the Mod</t>
    <t id="8">* When Lacuna Notebook is opened, the Encyclopedia icon in the top bar displays as\n  active instead</t>
    <t id="9">Planned Features for Future Updates</t>
    <t id="10">* Addition of a back and forward button for navigating history like a browser\n* Support for jump entries, those entries with book icons that go instantly to an entry\n* Support for images and possibly videos in the entries</t>
    <t id="11">Viewing Entries Offline</t>
    <t id="12">* All content is generated from Markdown files in the docs/md_files directory of the mod\n* For example, in Windows, using the standard Steam X4 installation dir, the Markdown\n  files would be located in\n  + C:\\Program Files \(x86\)\\Steam\\steamapps\\common\\X4 Foundations\\extensions\\lacuna_nb\\docs\\md_files\n* Everythign is written to those Markdown files and then a script is used to convert it\n  to the 0001.xml t-file used by X4\n* Entries can also be customized, see "Customizing Entries in the Notebook" for info</t>
    <t id="13">Customizing Entries in the Notebook</t>
    <t id="14">* WIP</t>
    <t id="15">Contributing Changes to the Notebook</t>
    <t id="16">* WIP</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008004" title="Lacuna Notebook New Player Guide [Part 1] Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">Start Here</t>
    <t id="2">Welcome to X4!  If you're not already aware, X4 is a complex sandbox game that includes\nmany game mechanics.  Learning how to play this game will take patience and persistence.\nFor context, I streamed a few hundred hours of this game and even with the help of very\nknowledgeable viewers, I consider myself entry-level intermediate.\n\nBecause X4 is a sandbox, it can be easy to get lost in the beginning.  This guide has\nbeen designed to help you keep focus and stay on a pre-determined track that will\ngradually introduce game mechanics.  It's encouraged though that if you feel like going\noff and doing something else that interests you, then do eet.\n\nThe entries are all in order so when you're done with one, move on to the next.  That\nmeans next up, we have Guide Requirements.</t>
    <t id="3">Guide Requirements</t>
    <t id="4">This guide requires the following DLC:\n\n* Cradle of Humanity DLC \(Terran Faction\)\n\nI wanted to do a guide that required only the base game, but none of the missions\noffered with it are a good showing for new X4 players in my opinion.\n\nIf you only have the base game, this guide can still be followed but the sections\ninvolving the Terran DLC storyline will have to be skipped.  Also, nearly all the\nentries in Lacuna Notebook outside this guide apply to the base game.</t>
    <t id="5">DLC Overview</t>
    <t id="6">If you have all the DLC, you can skip to the next part of the guide.\n\nX4 has several DLC's available that add a substantial amount of content.  The DLC is\nnot required to receive updates for the base game though.  Nearly all new and changed\ngame mechanics are included as free updates to the base game and it will continue to\nreceive free updates.\n\n# Free DLC\n\nX4 includes a free DLC called "Ventures" that can be found by going to Settings &gt;\nOnline Features.  Ventures is an online feature where you dispatch ships that will\naccomplish missions in other players' games and you can get rewards from it.  The\nconcept sounds cool but I think it's currently disabled by Egosoft.  For this guide, we\nwill ignore Ventures and I do not recommended enabling it for now.\n\n# Major DLC's\n\nThe following DLC are in the major category because they offer a large amount of\ncontent such as:\n\n* New Game Starts\n* New ships\n* New sectors\n* New storylines/quests\n\nHere are the Major DLC's in order of release:\n\n1. Split Vendetta | Split Factions Focused | Released 2020-03-31\n2. Cradle of Humanity | Terran Factions Focused | Released 2021-03-16\n3. Tides of Avarice | Pirate &amp; Scavaneger Factions Focused | Released 2022-03-14\n4. Kingdom End | Boron Factions Focused | Released 2023-04-12\n5. Timelines | Non-Sandbox Scenario Missions Focused | Released 2024-06-20\n\nThe above DLC's are all included in the "Community of Planets Edition \(2024\)" bundle\nwhich goes on sale often and is an excellent value.\n\n# Ship Pack DLC's\n\nShip Pack DLC's are similar in content to Major ones, but are much smaller in size.\nThe following are the Ship Pack DLC's:\n\n1. Hyperion Pack | Main Addition is Hyperion Expeditionary Ship | Released 2025-02-20\n2. Envoy Pack | Main Addition is Envoy Stealth Frigate | Released 2025-09-10\n\n# Community of Planets Collector's Edition \(2024\)\n\nThe CoP CE Bundle is in this list because it does include two in-game items:\n\n1. The Yasur ship\n    + In the past, the Yasur could be obtained for free by participating in the\n      "Mutliverse Team Seasons" but that has been cancelled and no replacement has been\n      announced.\n2. Exclusive Paintmod: "Pearl Prospect"\n\nCoP CE does not have any story/quest content or adds new sectors.\n\n# Recommendations\n\nIf you like X4, I recommend all the DLC but if you have to choose, I've listed them in\nmy order of preference below:  \n\n1. Cradle of Humanity\n2. Kingdom End\n3. Split Vendetta\n4. Tides of Avarice\n5. Hyperion Pack/Envoy Pack\n6. Timelines\n7. Community of Planets Collector's Edition \(2024\)\n\nCommunity of Planets is last because it doesn't add much in-game content and is a more\nexpensive bundle.  If you want to support Egosoft though, go for it!</t>
    <t id="7">Initial Settings</t>
    <t id="8"># About Game Performance\n\nThe main hardware bottleneck for X4 is usually the CPU and not the GPU.  The CPU is\nresponsible for handling the realtime simulation of X4's dynamic universe.  There are\npersistent AI units all across universe engaging in mining, production, trade, war and\nother activities regardless of what the player is doing.  This is not a game where AI\nunits spawn in when the player is near and despawn when they leave.\n\nIf tweaking the display or graphics settings doesn't help with performance, then the CPU\ncould be the bottleneck.  Performance troubleshooting is a complex topic and beyond\nthe scope of this notebook though.  \n\nEgosoft does have the following post on their forum to help with performance\ntroubleshooting:\n\n[X4 Performance Troubleshooting Suggestions]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?t=420952\)\n\n# Display Settings\n\n1. Display Mode\n    + To enable seamless switching with alt+tab'ing, use "Borderless Window"\n2. Adjust everything else to your preference\n\n# Graphics Settings\n\n1. Adjust to your preference\n\n# Sound Settings\n\n1. Adjust to your preference\n\n# Game Settings\n\nGame Settings contains several settings that aren't clear until you've spent some time\nin the game.  Here are the ones I recommend adjusting for now:\n\n1. Autosave Interval: 10 - 20 min\n    + You will die often in this game so the shortest interval is recommended\n2. Auto-Roll: Off\n    + Auto-Roll automatically levels you which sounds nice, but it gets in the way.  Use\n      the roll left/right keybinds for a better experience.\n3. Boost Toggle: Off\n    + Definitely a preference, but I find holding it down makes it easier to control\n      boost in this game\n4. Maintain Speed in Menus: On\n    + You will be in menus a lot and it gets real annoying each time your ship slows\n      down while in a menu\n5. UI Scale\n    + Text to small or too big in menu's, adjust it here\n6. VE Goggles Auto Reset\n    + This setting will reset your zoom after a period of time which can be annoying if\n      you're watching something zoomed in\n\n# Accessibility Settings\n\n1. Adjust to your preference\n\n# Controls\n\nHere is the setting I recommend changing from the default:\n\n* Mouse Settings \(In the Main Controls Screen\)\n  1. Re-enable Mouse Steering: On\n      - Fixes the annoyance of re-enabling mouse sterring everytime you go into a menu\n\nThe Controls settings \(specifically General Controls\) is what you'll visit most often\nas you figure out how you want to map the game controls to your devices.  Feel free to\nadjust anything else but we will be revisiting Controls later in this guide.</t>
    <t id="9">Tutorial Time</t>
    <t id="10">X4 offers several tutorials to help familiarize yourself with the game, but I do not\nadvise doing them all before starting the game.  They have a lot of information, which\nis good but it's like drinking from a fire hose and can be difficult to retain the\nknowledge without in-game context.  This guide will advice which tutorials to take\nas you progress through it.\n\nFrom the Start Menu, select "Play Tutorials" and do the following tutorials which will\nhelp you with your first mission:\n\n* Basic Tutorials\n  1. Flight\n  2. Travel Mode\n      - Includes Autopilot\n  3. Combat\n* Intermediate Tutorials\n  1. Map\n  2. Missions\n  3. Spacesuit\n  4. Object Deployment\n  5. Long Range Scanning\n\nThere is a lot of information in those 8 tutorials \(especially for the Map\) but the good\nnews is they can be accessed at anytime in the game by press h.</t>
    <t id="11">Terran Cadet Game Start</t>
    <t id="12"># Lore Context for the Game Start\n\nX4 has a lot of lore \(including novels\) but for this Game Start, we'll keep it short to\njumpstart you into the X universe.  Here goes:\n\n* The X universe is populated by several alien races and each race also has several\n  factions\n* The main villians of X4 are the Xenon, a planet terraforming AI developed by the\n  Terrans of Sol several hundred years ago that have gone rogue\n  + The Xenon have mutated into space faring war machines that attack the other races\n* For the Terran Cadet Game Start, you will be part of the Terran Protectorate faction\n* The Terran Protectorate's highest priority is the desctruction of the Xenon and the\n  prevention of another AI that could become another Xenon-like threat\n  + They act independently and can be hostile towards other races if they intefere with\n    their objectives\n\n# Lets Start the Game\n\nX4 offers several Game Starts, especially if you have all the DLC.  For this guide, we\nwill start with "Terran Cadet."\n\nFrom the Start Menu, select "Start New Open Universe."  Select "Terran Cadet" under\n"Cradle of Humanity."</t>
    <t id="13">Terran Cadet | Mission 1 | Essential Work</t>
    <t id="14">Mission Tips:\n\n* Objectives will have a yellow color around them on the HUD\n  + If the objective is not in your view, there will be a yellow arrow pointing to\n    the direction of the objective\n  + Some objectives aren't specific objects but areas of space, you can view these\n    on the map\n* If you can't find where your objective is, check the map\n* Use Shift+Space to toggle mouse steering\n* Use Boost for short bursts of speed and Travel Drive for long-distance travel\n* If you forgot how to do something, tutorials can be accessed at anytime by presing h\n\nAfter the mission has ended, you have time to explore before starting the next one.\nWhen you're ready, proceed below to Mission 2.  You may also stumble into Mission 2\nduring your exploration.  If you encounter a cutscene, then you've started Mission 2.</t>
    <t id="15">Solborn Militia | Mission 1 | Defenders of Sol</t>
    <t id="16">Do the following tutorial:\n\n* Basic Tutorials\n  1. Highways and Gates\n\nTo start the next mission, fly through the Accelerator Gate in the Southern region of\nMars which will take you to the Asteroid Belt sector.\n\nAfter entering the Asteroid Belt sector, a cutscene will play and then you will be an\nimportant militia for Solborn Militia.  Accept the offer if you aready to do the next\nmission.\n\nMission Tips:\n\n* If you forgot how to do something, tutorials can be accessed at anytime by presing h\n\nFeel free to explore some more, mission 3 can be started at any time.</t>
    <t id="17">Solborn Militia | Mission 2 | Optional Mission: Time for an Upgrade</t>
    <t id="18">Start with the following tutorial:\n\n* Basic Tutorials\n  1. Docking\n* Intermediate Tutorials\n  1. Ship Upgrade\n\nThis Optional Mission will lead you to an Equipment Dock where ship upgrades can be\ndone.  You should have 185,000 credits in the bank so here are the upgrades I recommend:\n\n1. Engines: Combat Mk1\n2. Thrusters: Combat Mk1\n3. Shields: Shield Mk3\n    + It's expensive but it's a big upgrade over the Mk2, well worth it\n4. Software: Docking Computer Mk2\n    + Makes docking significantly easier, I always get this on ships I fly\n5. Repair your ship if needed\n\nYou should be able to afford the above upgrades, if not, prioritize the Mk3 Shield then\nthe Docking Computer Mk2 upgrades.\n\nHere are some important notes regarding ship upgrades:\n\n* Your ship can only be upgraded/repaired at Equipment Docks or Wharf stations\n  + Shipyards can only repair and upgrade Large \(L\) and Extra Large \(XL\) ships\n  + Generally, Equipment Docks offer cheaper for upgrades than Wharfs or Shipyards\n* There is no penalty for switching out equipment, feel free to swap out gear as much\n  as you want without additional cost\n\nAfter the upgrades are complete, feel free to explore as usual or proceed to the next\nsection.</t>
    <t id="19">Intermission 1 | Hotkeys Configuration Review</t>
    <t id="20">By now, you may have an idea if the default keybinds work for you or not.  You'll be\nspending a lot of time flying your ship around and doing combat so it's *really*\nimportant that the controls feel comfortable.  It really adds to the immersion when you\nstop thinking about what button to press but it takes awhile to get there also.\n\nIf the defaults feel fine, proceed to the next section, otherwise, hop on over to\nSettings &gt; Controls &gt; General and start making changes to see if you can find something\nthat feels more natural.\n\nThere are many controls to configure but here are the most frequent ones to start with:\n\n* Steering: Digital\n  + Strafe movement of your ship \(WASD\)\n  + Forward/Reverse Throttle\n    - Maybe use w &amp; s for forward/reverse throttle and x &amp; z for up/down instead\n  + Match Target Speed\n  + Stop Engines\n  + Boost\n  + Roll left/right\n* Modes\n  + Toggle Travel Mode\n  + Toggle Long Range Scan Mode\n* Target Management\n  + Target Closest Hostile\n  + Target Object\n* Misc\n  + Autopilot\n\nFeel free to configure other settings as you see fit, you can always return to this\nscreen.</t>
    <t id="21">Solborn Militia | Mission 3 | Wartime Economics</t>
    <t id="22">Mission Tips:\n\n* Prepare for mortal combat!  \n\nAfter the mission completes, proceed to the next section when you're ready.</t>
    <t id="23">Intermission 2 | Tutorial | Player Inventory, Illegal Wares, and Messages</t>
    <t id="24">Do the following tutorial:\n\n* Intermediate Tutorials\n  1. Inventory and Crafting\n      - Crafting can be ignored, it is a topic we'll cover later\n\nBy now, you may of sucked up some illegal items from destroyed ships.  You also may of\nencountered the Police stating they are scanning your ship for illegal wares.  As the\nname implies, illegal wares are prohibited in law-abiding systems.\n\nFor now, I recommend you drop any illegal wares that you may obtain.  It's not worth\nthe Police harrassment and we'll cover what to do with them later.\n\nThe other item I wanted to draw attention to is Messages which is a button on the same\nright-side bar as the Inventory.  You probably have some messages including offer\(s\)\nfor quests.  Like, the illegal wares, we'll ignore any offers from these messages for\nnow.  This is a big game and we still got plenty to cover.  Feel free to check for new\nmessages every now-and-then.\n\nWhen you're ready, proceed to the next section.</t>
    <t id="25">Solborn Militia | Mission 4 | An Exclusive Invitation</t>
    <t id="26">An exclusive invitation, what could it be?  Fly to the designated station and after\nyou dock, exit the ship and follow the yellow line.  If you noticed how much easier it\nwas to dock, that's the powah of the Docking Computer Mk2.\n\nAfter the meeting done, let's see you're in a huge time crunch and you have to get back\nto your ship ASAP.  The game has you covered: Press the Dock hotkey \(Default: Shift+D\)\nanytime to immediately return to your ship from anywhere on a station.\n\nOnwards to the next section when you're ready!</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008005" title="Lacuna Notebook New Player Guide [Part 2] Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">Project Genesis | Mission 1 | Maintenance Duty [Part 1]</t>
    <t id="2"># Mission 1 Pre-Start Items\n\nPart 2 of this guide covers "Project Genesis", a new plotline.  That name may sound\nfamiliar and that's because it's the other Game Start for the Cradle of Humanity DLC.\nPicking a Game Start in X4 does not lock you into the plotline for that Game Start.  In\nfact, you can experience all the plotlines offered by all the Game Starts no matter which\nGame Start you choose.\n\nBefore you take off from the dock, do the following:\n\n* Repair your ship if needed\n* Upgrade the engine to a Travel Engine Mk2\n  + You lose out on boost stats, but the travel drive spool up time to get to maximum\n    speed is greatly reduced and the travel speed is significantly faster.  Both of\n    these stats will be useful for this mission.\n* Purchase 2 Apprentice Service crew members\n  + We'll use them for later\n\nThis mission is focused on exploration and discovering a path to the objective.  The\nfinal destination is in a sector that is not shown on your map.  Here are some tips to\nhelp you discover the route to the final destination:\n\n# Using the Mission Ticker to Navigate to the Destination\n\nThe Mission Ticker in the lower-left shows two important lines regarding your\ndestination:\n\n* Objective Line \(&gt;\)\n  + The top "&gt;" line always shows the objective\n  + For this mission, it's "&gt; Fly to: Oberth"\n* Recommended Next Action Line \(&gt;&gt;\)\n  + The bottom "&gt;&gt;" line is the recommended next action for the objective\n  + For this mission, a couple of recommended actions will appear:\n  + "&gt;&gt; Fly to: Asteroid Belt"\n    - After completing the recommended action, it will update to the next recommended\n      one. An example is after reaching Asteroid Belt, it will change to\n      "&gt;&gt; Fly to: Jupiter" for this mission.\n  + OR\n  + "&gt;&gt; Find way to: Saturn 1"\n    - If the next recommended sector is not in your map, then the recommended action\n      will change from "Fly to:" to "Find way to:"\n    - The gate for the next recommended sector will always be in the sector you're\n      currently in, but it's up to you to find it\n    - There may be multiple gates to choose from also, so you will have to fly through\n      each one and check\n\n# Discovering the Path to the Oberon\n\nAuto-pilot can be used to automatically fly to the last known sector en route to your\ndestination.  For this mission, if you haven't done any additional exploration, then the\nauto-pilot will take you into Jupiter and then disengage because the gate for the next\nsector is not known.\n\n## Visually Finding Gates\n\nNow, the gate you need to go through next is in Jupiter, but you'll need to find where\nit is.  The easiest way to find a gate is to visually check around for an object that\nlooks like a gate and then fly towards it.  If only there was something that could help\nus zoom in and see objects far away.\n\nIntroducing Visual Enhancement Goggles, or VE Goggles for short.  Press y to zoom in\nand shift+y to zoom out.  If the zoom isn't working, make sure you're in Cockpit view\nand not External view.\n\nFrom here, rotate the ship around, zoom in with your googles, and see if you can spot an\nobject that looks like a gate.  If you can't spot one, it may be too far aware so you'll\nneed to explore the sector some more, zoom, and see if you can spot it.  Gates can be\nrelatively close to each other, or spread far apart, it varies from sector-to-sector.\n\nUsing the Long Range Scanner is an option as well, but it is limited to a 200km range\nwhich is actually a shorter distance than using the VE Goggles to visually spot gates.\n\nRepeat your chosen process until you reach the destination sector.  The X4 universe is\nhuge so expect to repeat this process often until you get all the sectors and their\nconnections mapped out.  That's part of the fun of exploration!\n\n# Deliver AGI Processor for Dr. Rick Feynman\n\nAfter you get close enough to the Oberon, you'll receive a fetch quest to get an AGI\nProcessor for Dr. Rick Feynman.  There are a few items to point out after you get this\ntask:\n\n* Check your Mission Manager \(Shift+M\) and you'll notice the mission has updated with\n  the new information and also a new Objective\n* Open the map and look at the station Dr. Rick Fenman points you to.  You'll notice\n  there is a hat with sunglasses and a yellow exclamation mark next to it.\n  + The hat withsunglasses means there is a mission-related person to speak with\n    - If you left-click on the station, it'll show the name of the mission-related\n      person; in this case, it's Pat Mason\n  + The yellow exclamation mark means the station has a mission objective\n    - Even if you mark the mission inactive, the icon will still be there but with\n      in a faded yellow color\n    - If you right-click on the station, there will be an option to "Show mission\n      \(Maintenance\) Duty" which will bring up the mission details\n    - The "Show mission ..." option applies to any object with a yellow exclamation mark\n      so you can see what mission it applies to\n\nBe sure to look at the Message Ticker box to see what the current objective is\n\(Top Line: &gt;\) and the recommended next action for it \(Bottom Line: &gt;&gt;\). And yes, like\nstations, ships can also have docks that you can land on.\n\nAs usual, when you complete the mission, feel free to explore before starting the new\none.  When you're ready, proceed to the next section.</t>
    <t id="3">Project Genesis | Mission 2 | Maintenance Duty [Part 2]</t>
    <t id="4">Do the following tutorial:\n\n* Intermediate Tutorials\n  1. Orders\n      - Includes setting Behaviour\n\nFor this mission, we're going to make use of one of the service members on our ship.\nWe've been piloting our ship the whole time but wouldn't it be nice to take a break?  If\nyes, I've got the solution for you!\n\nAny ship we fly can also be flown by a crew member we hire.  In order for someone to fly\na ship, they have to be promoted to Pilot for that ship.  Here is how we do that:\n\n1. Bring up Current Ship Info using the hotkey \(Default: Shift+Enter\)\n2. In the top button bar under "Information", press the "Crew" button\n3. Near the bottom of this menu is a section labeled "Full Crew List" which lists the\n   crewmembers currently assigned to the ship\n4. Press the "+" next to the crew member to fully reveal all their stats.  We're looking\n   for the one with the best "Piloting" rating i.e. the most stars.\n5. Check both crew members and see who has the highest rating \(we only care about\n   Piloting\)\n6. Right-click on that crew member and select "Promote to Pilot"\n    + The other service crew member can help with repairs to your ship when systems\n      get damaged.  We'll explore more about crew members later.\n7. Congratulations, you now have an NPC pilot for your ship!\n8. For the NPC pilot to take over, you have to get your butt off the pilot's seat using\n   "Get Up from Chair" hotkey \(Default: Ctrl+d\)\n9. Once you leave your chair, the NPC pilot will show up from God knows where and plant\n   their butt on the pilot's seat\n\nAs show in the Orders tutorial, you can now select your shop from the map and issue\norders to the pilot. What separates the NPC pilot from using Autopilot is:\n\n* The NPC pilot can dock at ships or stations\n* You can order the ship around to do things even if you're not on it\n\nSo now you have the option to let the NPC pilot fly your ship around.  The NPC pilot\ncan't do everything you can so you'll still have to take over, but they're great when\nyou need to dock at a station far away.\n\nTo take over piloting your ship, walk up to the NPC pilot and press the "Interact"\nhotkey \(Default: f\) to "Take Command of Ship."\n\nTry to order the NPC pilot to each of the objectives for this mission.\n\nComplete the mission and when you're ready, proceed to the next section.</t>
    <t id="5">Project Genesis | Mission 3 | Maintenance Duty [Part 3]</t>
    <t id="6">Nothing new to introduce for this mission, just complete the objectives.\n\nProceed to the next section after the cinematic.</t>
    <t id="7">Boso Ta | Mission 1 | Displaced</t>
    <t id="8"># Intro\n\nThis mission introduces many concepts including ones I've added as part of the guide.\nSince a lot is covered, I've made a walkthrough to help learn the new concepts in\nmanageable chunks.\n\n# Part 1 - Welcome to Grand Exchange I\n\nJust when you thought everything was going smooth, bam, you get transported halfway\nacross the universe!  Open your map and you'll see you're in "Grand Exchange I" now.\nFor reference, you were previously in "Gaian Prophecy" \(to the east\) before getting\ntransported.\n\nFollow the directions from Boso Ta and float your way to the spaceship he sent over for\nyou.  \n\nAfter you arrive to your new ship, you'll be tasked with building a Dock for the\nasteroid station that transported with you.  As a bonus, you own an additional ship now\nwhich means you have a fleet of two ships!\n\n# Part 2 - The Player Headquarters \(PHQ\)\n\nThe asteroid station is now called "Grand Exchange 1 Headquarters" on the map.  This\nheadquarters is also known by another name, the PHQ or "Player Headquarters."  I'll\nrefer to it as the PHQ for the rest of the guide.\n\nOpen the map, right-click on the PHQ, left-click on "Plan Build" item.  The game will go\ninto a station building tutorial similar to the one followed earlier.\n\nThe first step of the tutorial is to choose a dock and **IT IS VERY IMPORTANT** that the\ndock you choose is the "1M6S Standard" one.  **DO NOT** choose the Terran ones!\n\nMaterials are needed to build the dock module and the other two docks require materials\nthat are significantly harder to aquire at this point in the game.  Without delving into\nit too much, the other two docks require materials that are only created by Terran\nproduction stations and they're on the other side of the universe.  \n\nContinue on with the tutorial.  When you get to the point to assign a Builder, don't\nworry if one doesn't show up on the map, we'll go hunting for it.\n\nIn the Station Building advanced tutorial we took earlier, it started out with\npurchasing a plot and building the station within the plot.  Think of the PHQ as having\na pre-allocated plot and instead of building in open space, everything is built around a\ngiant asteroid.\n\n# Part 3 - Building a Dock Module for the PHQ\n\nDo the following tutorial:\n\n* Advanced Tutorials\n  1. Station Building\n      - Remember what the Builder ship icon on the map looks like\n\nStations need two things to build new modules:\n\n1. Resources aka Wares \(I'll use Wares for the rest of this guide\)\n2. A Builder that uses the wares to build the new module\n\nOptionally, credits may be required if the wares cannot be produced by the station\nitself or they cannot be delivered by the player to the station.  Credits will be used\nby the station to purchase wares delivered by NPC traders.\n\nIn the tutorial, we gave the station credits to purchase the required wares from NPC\ntraders.  For this guide though, we'll supply the station with the constructions wares\nit needs ourselves.  Use the "Property Owned" hotkey \(Default: shift+P\) and you'll now\nsee the PHQ listed under "Stations &amp; Subordinates."  To access the station construction\nscreen, right-click on the PHQ and left-click on the "Plan Build" item.\n\nTo figure out what construction wares the station needs, look in the right windows for\nthe line:\n\n|+| Resources needed to complete changes\n\nExpand that line and you'll see we're only missing 108 Energy Cells to complete the\nconstruction of the dock.  Its time to take matters into our own hands and get those\nEnergy Cells.\n\nExit out of the construction screen and bring up the Property Owned menu\n\(Default: Shift+P\). Click the |+| to expand the line for the PHQ and you may notice a\nnew item listed there.  Specifically, this line in orange:\n\n|+| Dock Modules \(0%\)      ! 0:40:00\n\nThe above line is the progress for the Dock Module and has the following progress\nstates:\n\n1. When no Builder is assigned and required wares are unfulfilled, the line will be\n   ornage with an exclamation mark\n2. When a Builder is assigned but required wares are unfulfilled, the line will remain\n   orange with the exclamation mark but the timer will reduce from 40 minutes to 8\n   minutes\n3. If the required wares are fulfilled, but no Builder is assigned, the line will turn\n   white and the timer will remain at 40 minutes\n4. When the Builder is assigned and the wares are fulfilled, the line will turn white,\n   the timer will reduce from 40 minutes to 8 minutes and the countdown will begin\n\nThe offer is open for NPC Traders to deliver the Energy Cells and we'll know if they've\nbeen delivered if the progress line changes to a white color.  But we're going to beat\nthem to get the Energy Cells delivered first, right?  Right...?\n\n# Part 4 - Faction Relations and Who Doesn't Like You\n\n* References:\n  + [Egosoft Wiki | Reputation Effects]\(https://wiki.egosoft.com/X4%20Foundations%20Wiki/Manual%20and%20Guides/Objects%20in%20the%20Game%20Universe/Factions/%28Player%29/Reputation%20Effects/\)\n\nDo the following tutorial:\n\n* Intermediate Tutorials\n  1. Faction Relations and Licenses\n\nIn the X4 universe, there are several races and each race has it's own factions.\nRelations are associated with factions, not with the race as a whole.  To view your\ncurrent faction relations, use the hotkey to open the Diplomacy Menu \(Default: n\).\n\nIn this menu, we have several items to observe:\n\n1. The color of the faction\n    + White: Neutral or Friendly\n    + Pink: Enemy\n    + Red: Hostile\n2. The Relation number/status\n    + This number affects how favorably a member of that faction responds to you in\n      communications and other activies as well\n    + -10 and below: Docking/trading with faction units is denied\n    + -20 and below: Faction ships/stations will attack all player combat ships\n    + -25 and below: Faction ships/stations will attack all player property\n3. The three-letter faction identifie:r\n    + When viewing objects on the map, the three-letter identifier is used for factions\n\nClose out of the Diplomacy Menu and open the Map.  On the Map, friendly objects are\nin a blue color instead of a white. Enemy and Hostile objects remain the same color of\npink and red.  \n\nThere are several ways to improve faction relations and a diplomacy system as well.  We\nwill cover those topics later as we have enough to do at the moment.\n\n# Part 5 - Using Comms to Ask for Directions\n\nTo get Energy Cells, we need to find a "Solar Power Plant" or a "Trading Station."\nTrading Stations are much more rare to find so we will focus on finding Solar Power\nPlants isntead.\n\nA Solar Power Plant may be near our PHQ already, or it may not, everyone's game is\ndifferent when it comes to what stations are in a sector.  For this guide, we will\nassume one is not nearby so we can cover how to find them.  Even if one is nearby,\nignore it and let's see if we can find another one with some exploring.\n\nSince we're in an unexplored part of the universe, let's get some assistance in finding\nwhere things are.  In X4, we can open Comms to other ships and ask them for directions\nto specific Points of Interests \(POIs\).\n\nHere is how communication works with another ship \(communication cannot be initiated\nwith stations\):\n\n* The ship you communicate with must be in radar range of the ship the player is\n  currently located in\n  + The player doesn't have to be piloting the ship, just aboard it\n  + NPC ships cannot communicate to other ships outside your radar range on your behalf\n* The ship must be a blue color\n  + You can communicate with pink/red ships as well but they provide any information\n* If asking for Directions, even if the ship is blue, there is a chance it will\n  decline to give you help based on your relation status\n  + If this happens, try another blue ship\n\nNow, let's find a ship to communicate with on the map:\n\n1. Make sure your ship is unselected, otherwise, a different set of actions shows up\n   when you right-click on the ship you want to open comms with\n2. Select any Teladi Company \(TEL\) ship in range of your player ship\n3. Right-click on it and left-click on Comm\n4. Ask "Where can I find...?"\n    + If they decline you, try again with another TEL ship\n5. Answer with "Way to: Wharf"\n\nIf all goes well, they'll send you the information and you'll now have a Guidance\nMission to get to the Wharf.  Check the Mission Ticker and you'll see the following:\n\nObjective Line: &gt; Fly to: Unknown Station\nNext Recommended Action Line: &gt;&gt; Fly to: Unknown Sector\n\nHere is the cool part about asking for directions specifically, this logic does not\napply to anything else.  If you use Autopilot, it will automatically take you to the\nstation, even if it's in an unknown part of space.  Because it only works with\nAutopilot, that means you'll have to pilot the ship because NPC's can't use autopilot\n\(a limitation of NPC pilots\).  Again, this only works if you're asking for directions\nand then use Autopilot to get there, otherwise it's the manual method of finding gates\nyourself like you did previously to find the Oberon.\n\nSo take over the ship, put on the Autopilot, and watch the scenery as it takes you to\nthe directed Wharf in Unknown Space.\n\n# Part 6 - Lookout for Builders and Solar Power Plants\n\nWhile the Autopilot is navigating there, open the map and watch for the following:\n\n* Solar Power Plants\n* Builders\n  + On the map, they are identified as a "Construction Vessel" when you hover over their\n    icon\n  + Their map icon looks like a tear drop/oval with a tail shaped like a diamond-shaped\n    heart\n\nHopefully both will show up on your way there.  The Solar Power Plant we can visit later\nbut if you see a non-hostile Builder, immediately right-click on it and select:\n\n"Hire for building &gt; Grand Exchange I Headquarters"\n\nIt does not matter if you don't have all the wares needed to build the dock module, the\nBuilder will wait at the station until you do.\n\n# Part 7 - Deploying a Sattelite to Maintain Trade Information for Wharf\n\nEventually the Autopilot will take you to the sector "Windfall I Union Summit" and park\nyou near the "VIG Vigor Syndicate Wharf."  Along the way, we discovered a couple of new\nsectors.  After you arrive, open the Missions Menu \(Default: shift+M\), select the\n"Guidance Mission" button and abort the mission.  The Guidance Mission and it's yellow\nline will remain until we cancel it or replace it with a new Guidance Mission.\n\nWhile we're here, let's buy a couple of things from this shipyard and let's our NPC\nPilot do the driving.  When an NPC Pilot is in control, we can actually do the\npurchase from the map and the NPC Pilot will automatically take care of docking at the\nstation to get the items.  This applies to anything we want to buy for ship upgrades or\nequipment.\n\nFrom the Map, do the following:\n\n1. Select the Player Ship \(Kestral Sentinel\)\n2. Right-click on the Wharf\n3. Select "Upgrade / Repair at..."\n4. Purchase the following items under Consumables:\n    + Buy 1 Satellite\n    + Buy 2 more Flares to max out at 4/4\n      - Always max out your flares when you can\n\nAfter you confirm the order, the NPC Pilot will automatically dock at the Wharf and\nthe items will be transferred to the ship.  \n\nSince this is a Wharf / Equipment Dock we can buy things from, let's keep track of it\nfor future purposes.  After a station leaves radar range of ship, trade information is\nstill available for 5 realtime hours.  5 hours can pass by fast in this game so to\nensure we can buy from this Wharf at any time, let's drop a satellite near it.  \n\nSince our NPC Pilot is piloting the ship, here are the steps to deploy the Satellite:\n\n1. Open the map and select your Kestral ship\n2. Right-click on an empty space near the Wharf\n3. Under "Deploy at Position"\n    + Select Civilian &gt; Satellite\n4. Make sure the Wharf is within the sphere of the Satellite.  If it's not, you can\n   click and drag the ship icon in the center of the sphere to move the deployment of\n   the Satellite.\n\nExcellent, now we can buy from this Wharf at any time without worrying about the trade\ninformation timer expiring on it.\n\nNow, let's take a roadtrip on the Highway which we've only see in the "Highways and\nGates" Basic tutorial.  When you're ready, proceed to the next section.\n\n# Part 6 - Roadtrip to the Core Highway Network\n\nThe Core Highway isn't an option when asking for directions so we'll have to find it\nmanually.  The good news is the Highway is in an adjacent sector to the sector we're in,\n"Windfall I Union Summit."  The other good news is the gate is within VE Goggles zoom\nrange from the Wharf.  Explore the other gates to see what sector they connect to.\n\nOnce you reach the sector "Silent Witness I," you can access the Highway.  Open the\nmap and you'll see two thin blue lines in the middle.  That is our Core Highway Network,\nthat is where our future lies.  \n\nHaul your butt over to the Highway and converge on to one of the lanes \(doesn't matter\nwhich one\).  From here, enjoy the ride as the Highway takes you on a tour of unexplored\nsectors.\n\nNow, while we're cruising on the Highway, let's check on our Kukri that got left back\nin Terran Space when we got teleported with the Asteroid Station.\n\n# Part 8 - Using the Kukri NPC Pilot to Explore\n\nLuckily \(or was it planned...\), we got an NPC Pilot for our Kukri so we can still\ncontrol it even halfway across the Universe.  While we're cruising on the Highway, let's\ngive our Kukri something to do.\n\nRight now, there is no known path from where the Kukri is, "Gaian Prophecy", to where\nour PHQ is in "Grand Exchange I" but we can fix that.  Like we've done before, it's a\nmatter of finding the jump gates and making incremental progress in the direction of our\ndestination \(in this case, moving East\).  \n\nSince the Kukri has an NPC Pilot, our options for finding gates are different.  We've\ngot three methods we can try:\n\n1. Issue the Explore command to the NPC Pilot\n    + I generally don't recommend this command for exploration because it is very slow\n    + Exploration aside, the Explore command is the only command that can be used on\n      an NPC Pilot to order them through a gate to an Unknown Sector\n2. Issue multiple "Fly and Wait" to explore the sector\n    + Requires the most micro-management but can ensure you get full coverage of the\n      sector \(including the stations\)\n3. Follow NPC Trader ships and let them lead you to a gate\n    + This is the method I recommend and we'll use for the Kukri\n\n# Part 9 - Following NPC Traders to Find Gates in an Unexplored Sector\n\nHere are steps you can follow to use NPC Trader ships to find Gates:\n\n* Special Note about Issuing Orders for NPC Pilots\n  + When assigning orders to NPC Pilots, the newest order should overwrite the old but\n    that doesn't always happen.  If you encounter a situation where an NPC Pilot is\n    ignoring your new orders, it's most likely because the new orders are getting\n    queue'd behind an existing order\n  + If the NPC Pilot is not responding to new orders, try removing all orders and then\n    issue the new order again\n    - To remove all orders, right-click on the NPC ship and under the "Orders" section,\n      select "Remove all orders" or "Remove all orders and assignments"\n    - Assignments refers to the "default behavior" and the above command resets the\n      default behavior to "Hold Position"\n\n1. Fly the Kukri to the center of the sector\n2. Once the center is reached, check for Trader ships \(ships with Trader, Freighter,\n   Delivery, etc... in their name\) that are heading East.  \n    + If no ships are here, keep moving East until you find a Trader moving East also\n    + Focus on Traders for this method, avoid tailing other ships such as Builders,\n      Miners or Scavanegers\n3. When a Trader moving East is spotted, with the Kukri select, right-click on the\n   Trader ship and select "Follow until further notice"\n4. If we're lucky, the ship will take us to the gate to the next sector but the NPC\n   Pilot will not follow them through a gate to an Unknown Sector\n    + If we're unlucky, the ship actually takes us to a gate away from our destination\n    + It's also possible that the ship we're following is faster than the Kukri and\n      went through the gate before it showed up in range of the Kukri's radar.  If that\n      happened, just find another ship to following going in the same general direction.\n    + Using this method takes some experience in figuring out if a ship is going to\n      lead us through a gate but once you get the hang of it, finding gates using NPC\n      Pilots become significantly easier.\n5. Give the Kukri the order to Explore the gate\n    + If the Kukri is now following the order, check the Special Note above about\n      issuing orders to NPC Pilots\n    + Explore is used because Fly and Wait can't be used to traverse gates to Unknown\n      Sectors\n6. Repeat the process in the next sector\n    + There won't always be a gate to take us East in the Universe.  Sometimes we'll\n      have to go North, or South, or even West and then move East from there.  Watching\n      the Trader flow of traffic helps us determine which positions the gates are in the\n      sector.\n\nGetting the Kukri to "Grand Exchange I" is purely optional and more of something to do\nwhen we have downtime with the Kestral \(such as when its traversing the Highway\).\nMultitasking during travel downtime is a common task in X4, especially as the empire\ngrows.\n\nCareful also about leaving the Kukri out in the open.  Once it leaves Terran space, it\nis much vulnerable to attack by hostile factions.  An often occurence in X4 is you'll\nget distracted by something and when you come back to check on your ship, it's been\ndestroyed.  Having the Kukri dock at a station while you're doing other things will keep\nit protected.  Also, always be saving!\n\n# Part 10 - Finding Energy Cells Sell Offers\n\nDo the following tutorials:\n\n* Intermediate Tutorials\n  1. Trade Orders\n      - Includes Trade Filter\n\nChecking back on the Kestral, it should of completed several trips on the Highway by\nnow.  During those trips, it will have mapped out all the stations picked up by it's\nradar.  Between navigating to the Wharf, then to the Highway, then taking a round-trip\non the Highway, hopefully a Solar Power Plant popped up somewhere on the map.  \n\nTo find a Solar Power Plant, we could manually browse through the map, or we could use\nthe Trade Filter to show us which stations are selling Energy Cells.  If we did find a\nSolar Power Plant or a Trading Station that sells Energy Cells, it'll show up on the\nTrade Filter.\n\nTo find a station selling Energy Cells, do the following:\n\n1. Open the map\n2. Enable the Trade Filter if it's not already enabled \(Default: 1\)\n3. Search for "Energy Cells"\n4. With the map centered on the PHQ, zoom out until you see a sell offer for\n   Energy Cells.  The more you zoom out, the more offers you may see but we want the\n   one that is closest to the PHQ\n5. Close out of the map once you've located the station you want to buy Energy Cells\n   from\n\nIf you no sell offers for Energy Cells popped up, proceed to the next section, otherwise\nyou can optionally skip it and go to the section after.\n\n# Part 11 - Following NPC Energy Traders to Find Solar Power Plant Stations\n\nIn the very rare case no sell offers for Energy Cells can be found, we do have another\nfamiliar method we can employ to find one.  Similar to how we followed traders to find\nwhere a gate is in a sector, we can follow "Energy Traders" to find where a Solar\nPower Plant is.\n\nIn X4, an NPC trader's name correspond to the type of wares they're trading in.  For\ntraders dealing with Energy Cells, they'll have either "Energy Trader" or\n"Energy Freighter" in their name.  Following one will lead you to either a station\nit's delivering Energy Cells to, or a Solar Power Plant that it's going to buy Energy\nCells from.\n\nSimilar to following NPC Traders for the Kukri, if the trader goes into an unexplored\nsector, you will have to manually issue the Explore order to traverse the gate and\nthen issue the follow order again to keep following it.\n\nOnce a Solar Power Plant has been found, proceed to the next section.\n\n# Part 12 - Purchasing and Delivering Energy Cells to Complete the Dock Module\n\nDo the following tutorials:\n\n* Intermediate Tutorials\n  1. Trading\n\nOpen the Property Owned menu \(Default: Shift+P\) and see if construction has started, or\nmaybe even finished for the Dock Module.  It's possible NPC Traders delivered the\nneeded Energy Cells while we were exploring.\n\nIf Energy Cells are still needed, then buy them from the nearest Solar Power Plant.\n\nDelivering the Energy Cells to the PHQ is a different than a normal trade.\nSpecifically, all stations have something called a "Build Storage."  Like the name\nimplies, the Build Storage is specifically used to store wares for construction.  A\ncommon mistake for new players is to deliver the wares to the station instead of the\nBuild Storage.\n\nAfter the Energy Cells have been purchased, here are the steps to deliver them to the\nPHQ's Build Storage:\n\n1. Select the Kestral\n2. Right-click on the PHQ\n3. Select "Transfer wares with Build Storage"\n    + The difference between Trade and Transfer is the menu presented for transferring\n      the wares.  The Transfer menu will show all wares currently needed for module\n      construction and the amounts needed for each ware.\n4. After the transfer is complete \(and assuming a Builder has been assigned and has\n   arrived at the PHQ\), the construction shall commence!\n\nWhile the Dock module is constructing, try exploring some more with the Kukri.\n\n# Part 13 - Dock Module Completed\n\nWhen the Dock Module is completed, we'll be contacted by Boso Ta to land on the newly\ncreated dock for our PHQ.  Land the Kestral on the dock and look around, you've just\nlanded your ship on your first station.\n\nFollow Boso Ta's instructions which will lead to the next mission.  When ready, proceed\nto the next section.  Finally, woohoo!</t>
    <t id="9">Boso Ta | Mission 2 | Escape Plan</t>
    <t id="10"># Part 1 - Navigating to Hewa's Twin V\n\nIn addition to specific POIs, asking for directions can also be used to create a\nguidance mission to an unknown sector.  For this mission, we need to find a way to\n    "Nopileos' Fortune VI" which will show up with a Blue Dot on the ask for directions\n    screen\n    - This function only applies when you're given a mission and it has an unknown\n      sector in the route.  We could of used this method when navigating to the\n      Oberth, but I wanted you to do it the hard way first :p.\n    - You will have to use the Hard way if a mission isn't given for your destination\n  + Bottom Line changes from &gt;&gt; Find a way to: Napiloeos to &gt;&gt; Fly to: Napileos\n  + Once we got the directions, we can use Autopilot to get there or direct our NPC\n    Pilot to Explore the gate\n    - For some reason, the Autopilot won't automatically fly through the gate to an\n      unknown sector in this scenario, even though it worked with getting to the wharf\n      in the last mission, so each time you encounter a gate to an unknown sector,\n      you'll have to fly through it manually\n  + Eventually we hop on to a very familiar Highway\n  + Eventually make it to "Hewa's Twin V"\n\n# Part 2 - Claiming an Abandoned Medium Ship\n\n  + If you're using an NPC Pilot, he will notify you an abandoned ship was found when\n    you get near the objective\n    - If you're piloting, the game may show a prompt to "Start the capturing tutorial to\n      learn about taking over a ship."  This tutorial doesn't exist...\n  + Use the travel downtime to explore more with the Kukri\n  + Order your Kestral back to PHQ after capping M-class ship\n  + Escore the Prometheus ship after it launches from the station\n  + Navigate with Kukri during downtime\n  + Dock at PHQ, admire your beautiful M-sized ship\n  + Follow the yellow line\n  \nDo the following tutorials:\n\n* Intermediate Tutorials\n  1. Signal Leaks\n      - Includes ship &amp; spacesuit scanning</t>
    <t id="11">Boso Ta | Mission 3 | Scientific Freedom</t>
    <t id="12">* Research teleportation first\n* Get 1 crew for Medium ship\n  + On the way, Delilah should contact us\n  + Make crew pilot for Medium ship\n* Find a path from Terran space to Grand Exchange I with Kukri\n* Make note contraband can be stored in PHQ\n* Speak with Delilah and she will give you two additional plotlines to follow:\n  1. Terran Covert Operations\n      - Dal Busta mission\n  2. Yaki Investigations</t>
    <t id="13">Terran Covert Operations | Mission 1 | Terran Preparations</t>
    <t id="14">* Sell Kestral parts to raise funds for station items\n* While we're in Terran space, let's get the wares we need before doing Covert Ops\n  mission\n* Send Kukri back to Terran space to help buy wares if Medium ship's cargo can't hold\n  them all\n  + The Gorgon could hold everything but 6 silicon carbide\n* Buy Computronic Substrate &amp; Silicon Carbide for station construction wares\n* Use Kestral to supply energy cells\n* Be sure to queue up transfer to Build Storage orders\n* Open Plan Build for station\n  + Under "Build Resources", expand "Resources needed to complete changes" and you'll\n    see your ships listed there as in-progress delivery of the wares\n* Get teleporter wares</t>
    <t id="15">Yaki Investigation | Mission 1 | A Pirate's Trail</t>
    <t id="16"></t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008006" title="Lacuna Notebook Returning Player Information Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">X4 Updates Notes for Version 7.0 Releases</t>
    <t id="2"># 7.0 and Timelines DLC | Released 2024-06-20\n\n* [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/4175480236654769488\)\n* [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5233225#p5233225\)\n\n## 7.0 Notable Changes\n\n* Reimagined Teladi and Argon Capital Ships\n* New sectors and landmarks\n* Redesigned Xenon models PE and SE\n* Debut of several Terraformer ships\n* Introduction of flyable Xenon ships\n* Added "Existential Crisis" endgame challenge\n* New Feature: Visual Enhancement Goggles that let you zoom in on the action\n* New Features: FOV Slider and new accessibility options\n\n# 7.10 | Released 2024-08-08\n\n* [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/4359005727097908057\)\n* [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5244714#p5244714\)\n\n## 7.10 Notable Changes\n\n* Several fixes and minor improvements\n* No notable new features\n\n# 7.50 Flight Model Update and Hyperion Pack DLC | Released 2025-02-20\n\n* [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/546725769035907147\)\n* [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5267469#p5267469\)\n\n## 7.50 Notable Changes\n\n* Complete overhaul of ship flight dynamics\n* Boosting now has its own dedicated energy pool instead of using shield energy\n* Ship Rebalancing: Every ship in the game has been rebalanced, with refined engine,\n  thruster, and component interactions.\n* New Feature Behavior Inspection Mode: A new tool to analyse and adjust ship\n  behaviours, giving you the ability to diagnose and solve problems with the ships in\n  your fleet\n* Added Wide Sensor Array Module for Stations: A new radar station module enhances\n  detection capabilities, expanding your strategic awareness\n\n# 7.60 Technical Update | Released 2025-05-27\n\n* [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/541105143669589917\)\n* [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5279577#p5279577\)\n\n## 7.60 Notable Changes\n\n* Purely technical update focused on improving video memory management, along with a\n  range of bug fixes and optimizations to enhance stability and overall performance</t>
    <t id="3">X4 Updates Notes for Version 8.00 Releases</t>
    <t id="4"># 8.00 Diplomacy Update and Envoy Pack DLC | Released 2025-09-10\n\n* [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/612045811444875943\)\n* [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5290377#p5290377\)\n\n## 8.0 Notable Changes\n\n* New Feature: A Diplomacy system built around three main components:\n  + Embassy Room: An embassy facility that can be unlocked at the Player Headquarters\n    \(PHQ\)\n  + Agents: A new class of hireable NPCs who can be specialised in negotiation or\n    espionage\n  + Diplomatic Interference: Diplomatic standing between NPC factions can now be\n    triggered or influenced\n* New Feature: DLSS Frame Generation</t>
    <t id="5">X4 Updates Notes for Version 9.00 Releases</t>
    <t id="6"># 9.00 Empire Update | Released 2026-06-10\n\n* [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/503982156237767751\)\n* [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5318116#p5318116\)\n\n## 9.0 Notable Changes\n\n* Major rebalancing of weapons and missiles\n  + Added dedicated missile launcher slots on some S/M ships\n* New Feature Travel Drive Stability System: M size and larger ships no longer drop out\n  of Travel Drive instantly after receiving any damage.  Instead, they are increasingly\n  difficult based on size to knock out of Travel Drive.\n  + [Dev Post on Egosoft Forum]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?t=474552\)\n* Mining Region Overhaul: Completely overhauled how resource areas are managed\n  + Removed the influence of resource probes on mining efficiency; they now indicate to\n    miners where to focus their efforts\n* New Feature Priority Orders: New UI functionality that allows instantly responsive\n  "RTS"-style orders to be issued\n  + Orders can be issued and queued from the map using [SHIFT] + [Right Click], while\n    Priority Orders can be sent with [CTRL] + [Right Click] and queued using\n    [CTRL] + [SHIFT] + [Right Click]\n* S and M Kha'ak wrecks can now be recycled into Allographyne which transmutes to\n  replace any ware in the production process\n* Engines and Shields are now integrated into S and M ship models\n  + Most equipment is now interchangeable between S/M ships of all commonwealth races\n* Added target elements for torpedoes\n* Added Ship Showroom Module: Allows players to store and display their favourite S and\n  M ships on stylish landing pads\n* Adjustments to the UI's visual style in all areas of the game\n* NPC factions can better utilize and expand upon predefined construction plans for\n  better station designs\n* New Feature: FSR Frame Generation</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008007" title="Lacuna Notebook Misc Guides Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">How to be a Jetpack professional in X4</t>
    <t id="2"># Credit: AkevaBanshee\n\n# Intro\n\n1. Go into settings and rebind the "Stop engines" keybind in Controls&gt;General Controls Settings. This will be important later.\n2. Drop a quicksave in case you get too far from the airlock or can't find it you can reload the save and try again.\n3. Now your outside take a quick moment to orient your self &amp; consider dropping a "start guidance to target" marker on your ship so you know where its at and how far away. Optional since you dropped a quicksave.\n4. Now your outside get used to the controls. The spacesuit will tend to drift around. The circular radicle indicates your direction of travel, but it can be offscreen. If this happens hit the boost button to get it back in front of you. But be careful not to be facing a wall or a ship. If you are that's where the Keybind "Stop engines" come in.\n5. Returning to the airlock and docking. All you need to do is get close to the ship and either right click it bringing up the context menu or \(default keybind\) Shift+D and a green docking hologram &amp; docking lights will appear.\n\n# Additional Notes\n\n- Make liberal use of the Boost and Stop Engines keybinds to enhance your maneuverability and navigate tight corners.\n- Stop Engines is great for stopping drift and preparing for quick changes in directions.\n- Boost is good for quickly changing direction and minimizing drift.\n- Conder using alternate flight mode/steering mode \(default keybind\) Shift+Spacebar to toggle to the smooth steering. Use what one feel most comfortable.\n- I would recommend going into settings and turning off "Auto-Roll" This can cause vertigo in some players and in space Up-Down is what you decide it is, or how your brain interprets it. At least try this setting to see if it works for you. It's found under Settings&gt;Game Settings&gt;Auto-roll\n- Suit has more than 30 IRL minutes of power. Don't worry about it too much and if you feel anxiety about it remember it's a game and you dropped a quicksave.</t>
    <t id="3">UI Icons</t>
    <t id="4">Wtf do they all mean!  Also, not sure if this is something I can document easily in just\nMarkdown.</t>
    <t id="5">Faction Relations Improvement Speedup</t>
    <t id="6">Keep trading between the same stations</t>
    <t id="7">Speed up Crew Leveling</t>
    <t id="8">Keep trading between the same stations</t>
    <t id="9">Fixed Font Markdown Table Test</t>
    <t id="10">|1234567890|1234567890|1234567890|\n|----------|----------|----------|\n|a2b4c6d8e1|1!3@5#7$9%| 2 4 6 8 0|</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008008" title="Lacuna Notebook Spoilers - You Know You Want to Peak Inside Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">[Spoilers] List of Plot/Quest/Story Missions</t>
    <t id="2">References\n* [Egosoft X4 Wiki - Plots]\(https://wiki.egosoft.com/X4%20Foundations%20Wiki/Manual%20and%20Guides/Objects%20in%20the%20Game%20Universe/Plots/\)\n* [Fandom X4 Wiki]\(https://x4-foundations-wiki.fandom.com/wiki/Plots\)\n\n# Base Game Plotlines\n\n* Hatikvah Trade Revolution\n  + Start Trigger: \n  + Subplots:\n  + Dal Busta Influence: \n* Player Headquarters \(PHQ\)\n* Paranid Civil War\n\n# Split Vendetta DLC Plotlines\n\n* Free Families Conflict\n\n# Cradle of Humanity DLC Plotlines\n\n* Covert Operations\n* Segaris Terraforming\n* Yaki Investigation\n  + Subplots: Solborn Militia\n\n# Tides of Avarice DLC Plotlines\n\n* Empyrean Curs\n* Northriver\n\n# Kingdom End DLC Plotlines\n\n* Boron Reunification\n\n# Timlines DLC Plotlines\n\n* Timeline Scenario Graphs\n\n# Hyperion Pack DLC Plotlines\n\n# Envoy Pack DLC Plotlines</t>
    <t id="3">[Spoilers] List of Abandoned/Claimable/Derelict/Ownerless Ships</t>
    <t id="4">Excellent Detailed Steam Guide:\n* [All Ownerless Ships in X4: Foundations \(9.00 Base Game + All DLCs\)]\(https://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id=3273256652\)\n\n# Base Game Ships\n\n* Courier Vanguard in Nopileos' Fortune II\n* Drill Vanguard in The Void\n* Elite Vanguard in Grand Exchange I\n* Odysseys Vanguard in Faulty Logic VII\n* Osprey Vanguard in Company Regard\n* Perseus Vanguard in Silent Witness XII\n\n# Cradle of Humanity\n\n* Shinnamon's Gladius is abandoned by the gate to Savage Spur after he is kidnapped in the Terran Cadet plotline\n\n# Kingdom End Ships\n\n* Group in Watchful Gaze\n\n# Timelines Ships\n\n* Cutlass in Heretic's End\n  + Unlock Method: Graph 6: Signal Strength\n* Elite Sport in CEO's Doubt\n  + Unlock Method: Graph 1: nodus Asteroid Dash\n* Kestral Sport in CEO's Doubt\n  + Unlock Method: Graph 3: nodus Spaceport Stride\n* Odachi in Getsu Fune\n  + Unlock Method: Graph 6: terminus Flight of the Dragonfyre\n* Sapporo in Mists of Artemis\n  + Unlock Method: Graph 6: terminus Flight of the Dragonfyre\n* Theseus Sport in Moo-Kye's Revenge\n  + Unlock Method: Graph 5: nodus Station Circuit\n* Xenon B in Antigone Memorial\n  + Unlock Method: Graph 2: terminus Attack on Antigone\n* Xenon F in Nopileos' Fortune II\n  + Unlock Method: Graph 1: nodus Impeded Extraction\n* Xenon H in Nopileos' Fortune II\n  + Unlock Method: Graph 1: terminus The Fade\n\n| Kingdom End  | Group             | Watchful Gaze        |</t>
    <t id="5">[Spoilers] List of Plot/Quest/Story Special/Unique Reward Ships</t>
    <t id="6">[Guide]\(https://x4-foundations-wiki.fandom.com/wiki/Free_Ships#Plot_Reward_Ships\)\n\n* Cradle of Humanity DLC Ships\n  + Geometric Owl\n* Tides of Avarice DLC Ships\n  + Astrid\n  + Erlking\n  + Raven\n* Kingdom End DLC Ships\n  + Hydra Regal\n* Timelines DLC Ships\n  + Dart\n  + Xperimental Shuttle\n* Hyperion Pack DLC Ships\n  + Hyperion\n* Envoy Pack DLC Ships\n  + Envoy\n\n| Required DLC       | Ship                | Trigger/Unlock         |\n| --------------     | ------------------- | ---------------------- |\n| Cradle of Humanity | Geometric Owl       | Segaris Terraforming Plot   |\n| Tides of Avarice   | Astrid              | Northriver Plot            |\n| Tides of Avarice   | Erlking             | Northriver Plot            |\n| Tides of Avarice   | Raven               | Northriver Plot|\n| Kingdom End        | Hydra Regal         | Boron Reunification Plot         |\n| X4: Community of Planets Collector's Edition - Bonus Content | Yasur*** | |\n| Timelines          | Dart                | Finish Timelines DLC &gt; Go into sandbox game &gt; Wait for Boso Ta contact &gt; Quettanauts**          |\n| Timelines          | Xperimental Shuttle | Finish Timelines DLC &gt; Go into sandbox game &gt; Wait for Boso Ta contact &gt; Quettanauts            |\n| Hyperion Pack      | Hyperion            |                        |\n| Envoy Pack         | Envoy               |                        |\n\n* https://x4-foundations-wiki.fandom.com/wiki/Erlking#Recommended_Plots\n** Available for purchase after completing mission\n*** [Yasur Claim Steps]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5194251&amp;sid=b268a58a5e00f090becb0e8915634d2a#p5194251\)</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008009" title="Lacuna Notebook Homeless Content Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">Topic Ideas</t>
    <t id="2">* Low-Attention vs High-Attention\n* How sectors are laid out and the concept of the sector core\n* Diplomacy\n* What this guide isn't\n  + Min-maxing strats\n  + How to game the system by revealing the mechanics that should normally be outside\n    the player's knowledge</t>
    <t id="3">General Items</t>
    <t id="4">* Mines cannot be picked up, they have to be self-destructed if you want to remove them\n* What is the range of the tractor beam?\n* Make a note about the Signal Leak nearby, which could contain a hidden mission offerj\n* Document the different types of gates and highways\n* Are scans for illegal content RNG?  Sometimes I passed a scan, sometimes I didn't\n  for Terran Cadet Mission 6\n* How does Long Range scanning work for small objects?  Apparently the Mk1 does uses\n  different colors for different object types</t>
    <t id="5">Performance Considerations with Mods - Move to Modding Category When its Created</t>
    <t id="6">* Mods that add sectors or increase the number of ships or stations will also increase\n  the amount of things that need to be simulated on the CPU\n* Mods that add AI scripts will increase the CPU burden, especially if it's a script\n  that runs additional AI commands on every ship in the universe</t>
    <t id="7">Beginner Tips</t>
    <t id="8">* Use the Dock hotkey \(Default: Shift+D\) to immediately return to your ship from\n  anywhere in a station\n* Ships flown by NPC pilots do not benefit from Docking Computer software\n* Autopilot can only be used if the player is piloting a ship, it cannot be used by\n  NPC pilots\n* Only autopilot can be used to automatically travel to guidance points\n* Non-hostile ships in range of the player ship's radar can be asked for directions\n  to important Points of Interests \(POIs\).  Examples of these POIs are:\n  + Equipment Docks\n  + Faction Representative\n  + Shipyards\n  + Wharfs\n  + NOTE:  Even if a ship is not hostile, it may decline to help based on the relation\n    status.  If it declines, find another ship and repeat until you find one that does\n    help.\n* A trader is required to move wares between a station and it's Build Storage\n* Station Modules can be Free Floating, it is optional to have connected/snap together\n  + Use of snapping helps keep a order/structure when adding a lot of modules\n* Travel Drive can be used to match speeds with targets that are faster than your\n  standard engine speed\n* Hold down shift while rotating modules to rotate them in 15 degree increments</t>
    <t id="9">Veteran Tips</t>
    <t id="10">* Defence Drones are not shown in low-attention but they do contribute damage\n* Use the Protect Position, Explore sphere sliders to guage distance between two objects\n* When explore command is used on a gate, the radius is smaller than when used on empty\n  space \(350km\)\n* Disable maroon protection to stop "Wait for Signal" when NPC Pilot takes over, risks\n  him taking off without you</t>
  </page>
</language>
