<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<language>
  <page id="698008001" title="Lacuna Notebook General Info" descr="" voice="no">
    <!-- In-Encyclopedia Category Name -->
    <t id="99">Lacuna Notebook</t>
    <!-- Left Sidebar Button Name -->
    <t id="2400">Lacuna Notebook</t>
    <t id="2401">The Lacuna Notebook contains community provided information to further explain game topics not covered in the in-game documentation</t>
    <!-- Detail/References Pane Title-->
    <t id="2404">References</t>
    <!-- Top Level Menu Button Name -->
    <t id="8104">Lacuna Notebook</t>
    <t id="8107">The Lacuna Notebook contains knowledge that you have acquired and lists historic events on a timeline.</t>
    <!-- Menu Title -->
    <t id="9000">Encyclopedia + Lacuna Notebook</t>
  </page>
  
  <page id="698008002" title="Lacuna Notebook Categories" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">Welcome to Lacuna Notebook</t>
    <t id="2">698008003</t>
    <t id="3">New to X4 Guide</t>
    <t id="4">698008004</t>
    <t id="5">Returning to X4</t>
    <t id="6">698008005</t>
    <t id="7">Guides</t>
    <t id="8">698008006</t>
    <t id="9">Spoilers - You Know You Want to Peak Inside</t>
    <t id="10">698008007</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008003" title="Lacuna Notebook Welcome to Lacuna Notebook Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">Start Here</t>
    <t id="2">The goal of the Lacuna Notebook is to provide information that will help players get the\nmost out of their playthrough.  X4 is big, complicated, and obfuscated by lack of\ninstruction.  \n\nThe information provided in the Notebook entries tries to fill the gaps of in-game\ndocumentation but it will also include spoilers.  If the entry has spoiler information,\nit will have a [Spolier] tag at the beginning of the title.  A best-effort will be made\nto note if any entry has spoilers but sometimes it could be matter of opinion.  \n\nThe format of the entries is in Markdown style.  X4 has no support for rendering \nMarkdown content, but all the entries in the Notebook come from Markdown documents.  \nMore information can be viewed in the entries:\n\n- Viewing Entries Offline\n- Customizing Entries\n\nThis notebook is my first mod and is basically a copy of the Encyclopedia with code\nbolted on for Lacuna Notebook.  All the functionality and content of the vanilla\nEncyclopedia is in Lacuna Notebook also.\n\nThere is so much content I want to add that the organization of it will likely change\nas more entries get added.  I also want to make sure this mod doesn't break anything but\nno refunds :\)!  Expect lots, no, tons of typo, grammatical, and formatting errors to, no\nwait, too I mean...\n\nIf wondering where to go next, here are a couple of categories to visit next:\n\n- For new players, open up "New to X4"\n- For returning players, open up "Returning to X4"</t>
    <t id="3">Searching Information</t>
    <t id="4">- The search function works just like the one in the Encyclopedia\n- Searches are done only on the title of an entry, not the body/contents of it</t>
    <t id="5">Avoiding Spoilers</t>
    <t id="6">- A best-effort will be made to include the [Spoiler] tag in the title of any entry that\n  may have a spoiler</t>
    <t id="7">Known Issues with the Mod</t>
    <t id="8">- When Lacuna Notebook is opened, the Encyclopedia icon in the top bar displays as\n  active instead</t>
    <t id="9">Planned Features for Future Updates</t>
    <t id="10">- Addition of a back and forward button for navigating history like a browser\n- Support for jump entries, those entries with book icons that go instantly to an entry\n- Support for images and possibly videos in the entries</t>
    <t id="11">Viewing Entries Offline</t>
    <t id="12">- All content is generated from Markdown files in the docs/md_files directory of the mod\n- For example, in Windows, using the standard Steam X4 installation dir, the Markdown\n  files would be located in\n  - C:\\Program Files \(x86\)\\Steam\\steamapps\\common\\X4 Foundations\\extensions\\lacuna_nb\\docs\\md_files\n- Everythign is written to those Markdown files and then a script is used to convert it\n  to the 0001.xml t-file used by X4\n- Entries can also be customized, see "Customizing Entries in the Notebook" for info</t>
    <t id="13">Customizing Entries in the Notebook</t>
    <t id="14">- WIP</t>
    <t id="15">Contributing Changes to the Notebook</t>
    <t id="16">- WIP</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008004" title="Lacuna Notebook New to X4 Guide Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">Start Here</t>
    <t id="2">Welcome to X4!  If you're not already aware, X4 is a complex games that includes many\ngame mechanics.  Learning how to play this game will take patience and persistence.\nFor context, I streamed a few hundred hours of this game and even with the help of very\nknowledgeable viewers, I consider myself entry-level intermediate.\n\nThis guide is designed to help you keep keep focus and stay on a pre-determined track\nthat will gradually introduce game mechanics.  Be prepared for words, lots and lots of\nwords.\n\nThe entries are all in order so when you're done with one, move on to the next.  That\nmeans next up, we have Guide Requirements.</t>
    <t id="3">Guide Requirements</t>
    <t id="4">This guide requires the following DLC:\n\n- Cradle of Humanity DLC \(Terran Faction\)\n\nI wanted to do a guide that required only the base game, but none of the missions\noffered with it are a good showing for new X4 players in my opinion.\n\nIf you only have the base game, this guide can still be followed but the sections\ninvolving the Terran DLC storyline will have to be skipped.  Also, nearly all the\nentries in Lacuna Notebook outside this guide apply to the base game.</t>
    <t id="5">DLC Overview</t>
    <t id="6">If you have all the DLC, you can skip to the next part of the guide.\n\nX4 has several DLC's available that add a substantial amount of content.  The DLC is\nnot required to receive updates for the base game though.  Nearly all new and changed\ngame mechanics are included as free updates to the base game and it will continue to\nreceive free updates.\n\n# Free DLC\n\nX4 includes a free DLC called "Ventures" that can be found by going to Settings &gt;\nOnline Features.  Ventures is an online feature where you dispatch ships that will\naccomplish missions in other players' games and you can get rewards from it.  The\nconcept sounds cool but I think it's currently disabled by Egosoft.  For this guide, we\nwill ignore Ventures.\n\n# Major DLC's\n\nThe following DLC are in the major category because they offer a large amount of\ncontent such as:\n\n- New gamestarts\n- New ships\n- New sectors\n- New storylines/quests\n\nHere are the Major DLC's in order of release:\n\n- Split Vendetta | Split Factions Focused | Released 2020-03-31\n- Cradle of Humanity | Terran Factions Focused | Released 2021-03-16\n- Tides of Avarice | Pirate &amp; Scavaneger Factions Focused | Released 2022-03-14\n- Kingdom End | Boron Factions Focused | Released 2023-04-12\n- Timelines | Non-Sandbox Scenario Missions Focused | Released 2024-06-20\n\nThe above DLC's are all included in the "Community of Planets Edition \(2024\)" bundle\nwhich goes on sale often and is an excellent value.\n\n# Ship Pack DLC's\n\nShip Pack DLC's are similar in content to Major ones, but are much smaller in size.\nThe following are the Ship Pack DLC's:\n\n- Hyperion Pack | Main Addition is Hyperion Expeditionary Ship | Released 2025-02-20\n- Envoy Pack | Main Addition is Envoy Stealth Frigate | Released 2025-09-10\n\n# Community of Planets Collector's Edition \(2024\)\n\nThe CoP CE Bundle is in this list because it does include two in-game items:\n\n- The Yasur ship\n  - In the past, the Yasur could be obtained for free by participating in the\n    "Mutliverse Team Seasons" but that has been cancelled and no replacement has been\n    announced.\n- Exclusive Paintmod: "Pearl Prospect"\n\nCoP CE does not have any story/quest content or adds new sectors.\n\n# Recommendations\n\nIf you like X4, I recommend all the DLC but if you have to choose, I've listed them in\nmy order of preference below:  \n\n1. Cradle of Humanity\n2. Kingdom End\n3. Split Vendetta\n4. Tides of Avarice\n5. Hyperion Pack/Envoy Pack\n6. Timelines\n7. Community of Planets Collector's Edition \(2024\)\n\nCommunity of Planets is last because it doesn't add much in-game content and is a more expensive bundle.  If you want to support Egosoft though, go for it!</t>
    <t id="7">Gamestart Time! - Terran Cadet Start</t>
    <t id="8">Start Open Universe &gt; Cradle of Humanity DLC &gt; Terran Cadet</t>
    <t id="9">Settings</t>
    <t id="10">There are a lot of settings in X4 but for this guide let's get the following ones\nconfigured:\n\n- \n\nFeel free to poke around some more and when you're done, it's tutorial time!</t>
    <t id="11">Tutorial Time - Everyone Loves Tutorials!</t>
    <t id="12">X4 offers several tutorials to help familiarize yourself with the game, but I do not\nadvise doing them all before starting the game.  They have a lot of information, which\nis good but it's like drinking from a fire hose and can be difficult to retain the\nknowledge without in-game context.  This guide will advice which tutorials to take\nnext as you progress through it.\n\nTo start, complete the following tutorials:\n\n-</t>
    <t id="13">Adjusting Basic Controls</t>
    <t id="14"></t>
    <t id="15">About Game Performance</t>
    <t id="16">The main hardware bottleneck for X4 is usually the CPU and not the GPU.  X4 runs a\nrealtime simulation of thousands \(perhaps more\) ships and stations with their own\nagendas and it's all done on the CPU.  This simulation is always running, no matter\nwhat is happening in the game.  Even in a massive battle with hundreds of ships flying\naround, all firing their guns and missiles, the game is still doing the universe\nsimulation in the background in addition to simulating everything else going on within\nthe player's vicinity.\n\nIt is also worth noting that while X4 supports using multiple CPU cores, not all cores\nare utilized evenly.  Running a compelx simulation across multiple cores is very tricky because everything has to be in sync.  The safest and most stable route is to have\none core bear the burden of the simulation and let the other cores handle other\nindependent tasks.  This means though that despite having 16 cores, only one core is\ndoing most of the work.  Even Unreal Engine 5 locks game simulation to a single thread\n\(queue Unreal Engine performance mockery\).\n\n# Troubleshooting Performance\n\nThis is a whole giant topic that is beyond the scope of this Notebook.  Egosoft does\nhave the following post on their forum to help with Troubleshooting:\n\n[X4 Performance Troubleshooting Suggestions]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?t=420952\)\n\n# Performance Considerations with Mods - Move to Modding Category When its Created\n\n- Mods that add sectors or increase the number of ships or stations will also increase\n  the amount of things that need to be simulated on the CPU\n- Mods that add AI scripts will increase the CPU burden, especially if it's a script\n  that runs additional AI commands on every ship in the universe</t>
    <t id="17">Flight Controls</t>
    <t id="18">TBD</t>
    <t id="19">Tutorials</t>
    <t id="20">TBD</t>
    <t id="21">Game Starts</t>
    <t id="22">TBD</t>
    <t id="23">Terran Cadet</t>
    <t id="24">TBD</t>
    <t id="25">Player Headquarters \(PHQ\)</t>
    <t id="26">TBD</t>
    <t id="27">End Terran Cadet Story</t>
    <t id="28">TBD</t>
    <t id="29">Making Money</t>
    <t id="30">TBD</t>
    <t id="31">Mining</t>
    <t id="32">TBD</t>
    <t id="33">Trading</t>
    <t id="34">TBD</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008005" title="Lacuna Notebook Returning to X4 Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">X4 Updates Notes for Version 7.0 Releases</t>
    <t id="2"># 7.0 and Timelines DLC | Released 2024-06-20\n\n- [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/4175480236654769488\)\n- [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5233225#p5233225\)\n\n## Notable Changes\n\n- Reimagined Teladi and Argon Capital Ships\n- New sectors and landmarks\n- Redesigned Xenon models PE and SE\n- Debut of several Terraformer ships\n- Introduction of flyable Xenon ships\n- Added "Existential Crisis" endgame challenge\n- New Feature: Visual Enhancement Goggles that let you zoom in on the action\n- New Features: FOV Slider and new accessibility options\n\n# 7.10 | Released 2024-08-08\n\n- [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/4359005727097908057\)\n- [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5244714#p5244714\)\n\n## Notable Changes\n\n - Several fixes and minor improvements\n - No notable new features\n \n# 7.50 Flight Model Update and Hyperion Pack DLC | Released 2025-02-20\n\n- [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/546725769035907147\)\n- [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5267469#p5267469\)\n\n## Notable Changes\n\n- Complete overhaul of ship flight dynamics\n- Boosting now has its own dedicated energy pool instead of using shield energy\n- Ship Rebalancing: Every ship in the game has been rebalanced, with refined engine,\n  thruster, and component interactions.\n- New Feature Behavior Inspection Mode: A new tool to analyse and adjust ship\n  behaviours, giving you the ability to diagnose and solve problems with the ships in\n  your fleet\n- Added Wide Sensor Array Module for Stations: A new radar station module enhances\n  detection capabilities, expanding your strategic awareness\n\n# 7.60 Technical Update | Released 2025-05-27\n\n- [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/541105143669589917\)\n- [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5279577#p5279577\)\n\n## Notable Changes\n\n- Purely technical update focused on improving video memory management, along with a\n  range of bug fixes and optimizations to enhance stability and overall performance</t>
    <t id="3">X4 Updates Notes for Version 8.00 Releases</t>
    <t id="4"># 8.00 Diplomacy Update and Envoy Pack DLC | Released 2025-09-10\n\n- [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/612045811444875943\)\n- [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5290377#p5290377\)\n\n## Notable Changes\n\n- New Feature: A Diplomacy system built around three main components:\n  - Embassy Room: An embassy facility that can be unlocked at the Player Headquarters\n    \(PHQ\)\n  - Agents: A new class of hireable NPCs who can be specialised in negotiation or\n    espionage\n  - Diplomatic Interference: Diplomatic standing between NPC factions can now be\n    triggered or influenced\n- New Feature: DLSS Frame Generation</t>
    <t id="5">X4 Updates Notes for Version 9.00 Releases</t>
    <t id="6"># 9.00 Empire Update | Released 2026-06-10\n\n- [Relase Post on Steam]\(https://store.steampowered.com/news/app/392160/view/503982156237767751\)\n- [Changelog]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?p=5318116#p5318116\)\n\n## Notable Changes\n\n- Major rebalancing of weapons and missiles\n  - Added dedicated missile launcher slots on some S/M ships\n- New Feature Travel Drive Stability System: M size and larger ships no longer drop out\n  of Travel Drive instantly after receiving any damage.  Instead, they are increasingly\n  difficult based on size to knock out of Travel Drive.\n  - [Dev Post on Egosoft Forum]\(https://forum.egosoft.com/viewtopic.php?t=474552\)\n- Mining Region Overhaul: Completely overhauled how resource areas are managed\n  - Removed the influence of resource probes on mining efficiency; they now indicate to\n    miners where to focus their efforts\n- New Feature Priority Orders: New UI functionality that allows instantly responsive\n  "RTS"-style orders to be issued\n  - Orders can be issued and queued from the map using [SHIFT] + [Right Click], while\n    Priority Orders can be sent with [CTRL] + [Right Click] and queued using\n    [CTRL] + [SHIFT] + [Right Click]\n- S and M Kha'ak wrecks can now be recycled into Allographyne which transmutes to\n  replace any ware in the production process\n- Engines and Shields are now integrated into S and M ship models\n  - Most equipment is now interchangeable between S/M ships of all commonwealth races\n- Added target elements for torpedoes\n- Added Ship Showroom Module: Allows players to store and display their favourite S and\n  M ships on stylish landing pads\n- Adjustments to the UI's visual style in all areas of the game\n- NPC factions can better utilize and expand upon predefined construction plans for\n  better station designs\n- New Feature: FSR Frame Generation</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008006" title="Lacuna Notebook Guides Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">How to be a Jetpack professional in X4</t>
    <t id="2"># Credit: AkevaBanshee\n\n# Intro\n\n1. Go into settings and rebind the "Stop engines" keybind in Controls&gt;General Controls Settings. This will be important later.\n2. Drop a quicksave in case you get too far from the airlock or can't find it you can reload the save and try again.\n3. Now your outside take a quick moment to orient your self &amp; consider dropping a "start guidance to target" marker on your ship so you know where its at and how far away. Optional since you dropped a quicksave.\n4. Now your outside get used to the controls. The spacesuit will tend to drift around. The circular radicle indicates your direction of travel, but it can be offscreen. If this happens hit the boost button to get it back in front of you. But be careful not to be facing a wall or a ship. If you are that's where the Keybind "Stop engines" come in.\n5. Returning to the airlock and docking. All you need to do is get close to the ship and either right click it bringing up the context menu or \(default keybind\) Shift+D and a green docking hologram &amp; docking lights will appear.\n\n# Additional Notes\n\n- Make liberal use of the Boost and Stop Engines keybinds to enhance your maneuverability and navigate tight corners.\n- Stop Engines is great for stopping drift and preparing for quick changes in directions.\n- Boost is good for quickly changing direction and minimizing drift.\n- Conder using alternate flight mode/steering mode \(default keybind\) Shift+Spacebar to toggle to the smooth steering. Use what one feel most comfortable.\n- I would recommend going into settings and turning off "Auto-Roll" This can cause vertigo in some players and in space Up-Down is what you decide it is, or how your brain interprets it. At least try this setting to see if it works for you. It's found under Settings&gt;Game Settings&gt;Auto-roll\n- Suit has more than 30 IRL minutes of power. Don't worry about it too much and if you feel anxiety about it remember it's a game and you dropped a quicksave.</t>
    <t id="3">UI Icons</t>
    <t id="4">Wtf do they all mean!  Also, not sure if this is something I can document easily in just\nMarkdown.</t>
    <t id="5">Faction Relations Improvement Speedup</t>
    <t id="6">Keep trading between the same stations</t>
    <t id="7">Speed up Crew Leveling</t>
    <t id="8">Keep trading between the same stations</t>
  </page>
  <page id="698008007" title="Lacuna Notebook Spoilers - You Know You Want to Peak Inside Topics" descr="" voice="no">
    <t id="1">[Spoiler] List of Plot/Quest/Story Missions</t>
    <t id="2">References\n- [Egosoft X4 Wiki - Plots]\(https://wiki.egosoft.com/X4%20Foundations%20Wiki/Manual%20and%20Guides/Objects%20in%20the%20Game%20Universe/Plots/\)\n- [Fandom X4 Wiki]\(https://x4-foundations-wiki.fandom.com/wiki/Plots\)\n\n# Base Game Plotlines\n\n- Hatikvah Trade Revolution\n  - Start Trigger: \n  - Subplots:\n  - Dal Busta Influence: \n- Player Headquarters \(PHQ\)\n- Paranid Civil War\n\n# Split Vendetta DLC Plotlines\n\n- Free Families Conflict\n\n# Cradle of Humanity DLC Plotlines\n\n- Covert Operations\n- Segaris Terraforming\n- Yaki Investigation\n  - Subplots: Solborn Militia\n\n# Tides of Avarice DLC Plotlines\n\n- Empyrean Curs\n- Northriver\n\n# Kingdom End DLC Plotlines\n\n- Boron Reunification\n\n# Timlines DLC Plotlines\n\n- Timeline Scenario Graphs\n\n# Hyperion Pack DLC Plotlines\n\n# Envoy Pack DLC Plotlines</t>
    <t id="3">[Spoiler] List of Abandoned/Claimable/Derelict/Ownerless Ships</t>
    <t id="4">Excellent Detailed Steam Guide:\n- [All Ownerless Ships in X4: Foundations \(9.00 Base Game + All DLCs\)]\(https://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id=3273256652\)\n\n# Base Game Ships\n\n- Courier Vanguard in Nopileos' Fortune II\n- Drill Vanguard in The Void\n- Elite Vanguard in Grand Exchange I\n- Odysseys Vanguard in Faulty Logic VII\n- Osprey Vanguard in Company Regard\n- Perseus Vanguard in Silent Witness XII\n\n# Kingdom End Ships\n\n- Group in Watchful Gaze\n\n# Timelines Ships\n\n- Cutlass in Heretic's End\n  - Unlock Method: Graph 6: Signal Strength\n- Elite Sport in CEO's Doubt\n  - Unlock Method: Graph 1: nodus Asteroid Dash\n- Kestral Sport in CEO's Doubt\n  - Unlock Method: Graph 3: nodus Spaceport Stride\n- Odachi in Getsu Fune\n  - Unlock Method: Graph 6: terminus Flight of the Dragonfyre\n- Sapporo in Mists of Artemis\n  - Unlock Method: Graph 6: terminus Flight of the Dragonfyre\n- Theseus Sport in Moo-Kye's Revenge\n  - Unlock Method: Graph 5: nodus Station Circuit\n- Xenon B in Antigone Memorial\n  - Unlock Method: Graph 2: terminus Attack on Antigone\n- Xenon F in Nopileos' Fortune II\n  - Unlock Method: Graph 1: nodus Impeded Extraction\n- Xenon H in Nopileos' Fortune II\n  - Unlock Method: Graph 1: terminus The Fade\n\n| Kingdom End  | Group             | Watchful Gaze        |</t>
    <t id="5">[Spoiler] List of Plot/Quest/Story Special/Unique Reward Ships</t>
    <t id="6">[Guide]\(https://x4-foundations-wiki.fandom.com/wiki/Free_Ships#Plot_Reward_Ships\)\n\n- Cradle of Humanity DLC Ships\n  - Geometric Owl\n- Tides of Avarice DLC Ships\n  - Astrid\n  - Erlking\n  - Raven\n- Kingdom End DLC Ships\n  - Hydra Regal\n- Timelines DLC Ships\n  - Dart\n  - Xperimental Shuttle\n- Hyperion Pack DLC Ships\n  - Hyperion\n- Envoy Pack DLC Ships\n  - Envoy\n\n| Required DLC       | Ship                | Trigger/Unlock         |\n| --------------     | ------------------- | ---------------------- |\n| Cradle of Humanity | Geometric Owl       | Segaris Terraforming Plot   |\n| Tides of Avarice   | Astrid              | Northriver Plot            |\n| Tides of Avarice   | Erlking             | Northriver Plot            |\n| Tides of Avarice   | Raven               | Northriver Plot|\n| Kingdom End        | Hydra Regal         | Boron Reunification Plot         |\n| X4: Community of Planets Collector's Edition - Bonus Content | Yasur | |\n| Timelines          | Dart                | Finish Timelines DLC &gt; Go into sandbox game &gt; Wait for Boso Ta contact &gt; Quettanauts**          |\n| Timelines          | Xperimental Shuttle | Finish Timelines DLC &gt; Go into sandbox game &gt; Wait for Boso Ta contact &gt; Quettanauts            |\n| Hyperion Pack      | Hyperion            |                        |\n| Envoy Pack         | Envoy               |                        |\n\n* https://x4-foundations-wiki.fandom.com/wiki/Erlking#Recommended_Plots\n** Available for purchase after completing mission</t>
    <t id="7">Fixed Font Markdown Table Test</t>
    <t id="8">|1234567890|1234567890|1234567890|\n|----------|----------|----------|\n|a2b4c6d8e1|1!3@5#7$9%| 2 4 6 8 0|</t>
  </page>
</language>
